Now...
الآن...
let's go back in time.
فلنرجع بالزمن إلى الوراء.
It's 1974.
في سنة 1974.
There is the gallery somewhere
توجد صالة عرض في مكان ما
in the world,
في العالم،
and there is a young girl, age 23,
وتوجد فتاة شابة تبلغ من العمر 23 سنة،
standing in the middle of the space.
تقف في وسط الفضاء.
In the front of her is a table.
توجد أمامها طاولة.
On the table there are 76 objects
ويوجد عليها 76 جسما
for pleasure and for pain.
للمتعة والألم.
Some of the objects are
من ضمن بعض الأجسام
a glass of water, a coat, a shoe, a rose.
يوجد كأس ماء ومعطف وحذاء ووردة.
But also the knife, the razor blade, the hammer
كما يوجد سكين وشفرة حلاقة ومطرقة
and the pistol with one bullet.
ومسدس مع رصاصة واحدة.
There are instructions which say,
وتوجد تعليمات تقول،
"I'm an object.
"أنا جسم.
You can use everything on the table on me.
تستطيع أن تجرب كل جسم على الطاولة على جسمي
I'm taking all responsibility -- even killing me.
أتحمل المسؤولية كاملة -- حتى قتلي.
And the time is six hours."
والمدة هي 6 ساعات."
The beginning of this performance was easy.
بداية هذا الأداء كانت سهلة.
People would give me the glass of water to drink,
الأشخاص يعطونني كأس الماء لأشرب،
they'd give me the rose.
يعطونني وردة.
But very soon after,
ولكن بعد فترة وجيزة جدا،
there was a man who took the scissors and cut my clothes,
هناك رجل تناول المقص وقام بقص ملابسي،
and then they took the thorns of the rose and stuck them in my stomach.
ثم أخذوا شوك الورد وغرزوها بمعدتي.
Somebody took the razor blade and cut my neck and drank the blood,
أخذ أحدهم شفرة حلاقة وجرح رقبتي وشرب الدم،
and I still have the scar.
ومازالت لدي الندبة.
The women would tell the men what to do.
كانت النساء تُخبرن الرجال ما الذي يقومون به.
And the men didn't rape me because it was just a normal opening,
ولم يقم الرجال باغتصابي لأنه كان مجرد افتتاح عادي،
and it was all public,
وكان للعموم،
and they were with their wives.
وكانوا مصحوبين بزوجاتهم.
They carried me around and put me on the table,
حملوني ووضعوني على الطاولة،
and put the knife between my legs.
ووضعوا السكين بين ساقاي.
And somebody took the pistol and bullet and put it against my temple.
وأخذ أحدهم المسدس والرصاصة ووجهه نحو جسدي.
And another person took the pistol and they started a fight.
وأخذ شخص آخر المسدس ونشبت معركة بينهم.
And after six hours were finished,
وبعد انتهاء 6 ساعات،
I...
أنا....
started walking towards the public.
بدأت بالمشي نحو الجمهور.
I was a mess.
لقد كنت في فوضى عارمة.
I was half-naked, I was full of blood and tears were running down my face.
لقد كنت نصف عارية، ومغطاة بالدماء والدموع تنزل على وجهي.
And everybody escaped, they just ran away.
وهرب الجميع، لقد ركضوا بعيدا.
They could not confront myself, with myself as a normal human being.
لم يكونوا قادرين على التصدّي لي مع أني شخص عادي.
And then --
ثم --
what happened
ما الذي حصل بعد ذلك هو
is I went to the hotel, it was at two in the morning.
ذهابي للنزل، لقد كانت 2 صباحا.
And
و
I looked at myself in the mirror,
نظرت إلى نفسي في المرآة،
and I had a piece of gray hair.
حيث كان لديا خصلة من الشعر الرمادي.
Alright --
حسنا --
please take off your blindfolds.
من فضلكم أزيلوا عصابة العينين.
Welcome to the performance world.
مرحبا بكم إلى عالم العرض.
First of all, let's explain what the performance is.
أولا، فلنفسَر ما معنى العرض.
So many artists, so many different explanations,
العديد من الفنانين، والعديد من التفسيرات المختلفة،
but my explanation for performance is very simple.
ولكن تفسيري للعرض بسيط جدا.
Performance is a mental and physical construction
العرض هو البناء المادي والعقلي
that the performer makes in a specific time
الذي يقوم به المُؤدي في وقت معين
in a space in front of an audience
في مكان ما أمام جمهور
and then energy dialogue happens.
ثم يتولّد حوار ساخن.
The audience and the performer make the piece together.
يتشارك الجمهور والمُؤدي في تقديم المقطع.
And the difference between performance and theater is huge.
والفرق بين العرض والمسرح شاسع.
In the theater, the knife is not a knife
على المسرح، السكين ليس سكينا
and the blood is just ketchup.
والدم هو مجرد صلصة طماطم.
In the performance, the blood is the material,
خلال الأداء، الدم هو المادة،
and the razor blade or knife is the tool.
وشفرة الحلاقة أو السكين هي الأداة.
It's all about being there in the real time,
إن الأمر كله يدور حول الوقت الحقيقي،
and you can't rehearse performance,
ولا يمكنك التدرب على العرض،
because you can't do many of these types of things twice -- ever.
لأنه لا يمكنك القيام بهذا النوع من الأشياء مرتين -- أبدا.
Which is very important, the performance is --
والمهم جدا بخصوص العرض هو --
you know, all human beings are always afraid of very simple things.
كما تعلمون، كل البشر يخافون دائما من أشياء بسيطة جدا.
We're afraid of suffering, we're afraid of pain,
نحن نخاف من المعاناة، ونخاف من الألم.،
we're afraid of mortality.
ونخاف من الموت.
So what I'm doing --
اذن ما الذي أقوم به --
I'm staging these kinds of fears in front of the audience.
هو عرض هذه الأنواع من المخاوف أمام الجمهور.
I'm using your energy,
أنا استعمل طاقتكم،
and with this energy I can go and push my body as far as I can.
وباستعمال طاقتكم يمكنني تحدي جسمي أكثر.
And then I liberate myself from these fears.
وأتخلص من هذه المخاوف.
And I'm your mirror.
وأنا مرآتكم.
If I can do this for myself, you can do it for you.
إذا استطعت أن أفعل ذلك بنفسي، فأنتم تستطيعون ذلك.
After Belgrade, where I was born,
بعد بلغراد، أين وُلدت،
I went to Amsterdam.
ذهبت إلى أمستردام.
And you know, I've been doing performances
وكما تعرفون، كنت أقوم بالعديد من العروض
since the last 40 years.
منذ 40 سنة الماضية.
And here I met Ulay,
وهكذا تقابلت مع أولاي،
and he was the person I actually fell in love with.
وكان الشخص الذي وقعت في حبه.
And we made, for 12 years, performances together.
وقمنا بالعروض معا لمدة 12 سنة.
You know the knife and the pistols and the bullets,
كما تعرفون السكين والمسدسات والرصاص،
I exchange into love and trust.
أتبادل الحب والثقة.
So to do this kind work you have to trust the person completely
اذن لتقوم بهذا النوع من العمل عليك أن تثق بالشخص كليا
because this arrow is pointing to my heart.
لأن هذا السهم متجه إلى قلبي.
So, heart beating and adrenaline is rushing and so on,
اذن ارتفاع دقات القلب والأدرينالين وما إلى ذلك،
is about trust, is about total trust to another human being.
ترتبط بالثقة، الثقة العمياء بالشخص الآخر.
Our relationship was 12 years,
علاقتنا دامت 12 سنة،
and we worked on so many subjects, both male and female energy.
واشتغلنا على العديد من المواضيع التي تتطلب طاقة ذكورية وأنثوية.
And as every relationship comes to an end, ours went too.
وكما تنتهي كل العلاقات كان ذلك الحال بالنسبة لعلاقتنا أيضا.
We didn't make phone calls like normal human beings do
لم نقم باتصال هاتفي كما يقوم به الشخص العادي
and say, you know, "This is over."
ويخبرني "لقد انتهت علاقتنا".
We walked the Great Wall of China to say goodbye.
اتجهنا نحو سور الصين العظيم لكي نودع بعضنا البعض.
I started at the Yellow Sea, and he started from the Gobi Desert.
انطلقت من البحر الأصفر بينما انطلق من صحراء غوبي.
We walked, each of us, three months,
مشينا، كل واحد منا، 3 أشهر،
two and a half thousand kilometers.
2.5 آلاف كم.
It was the mountains, it was difficult.
كانت هناك الكثير من الجبال، كان ذلك صعبا.
It was climbing, it was ruins.
كنا نتسلق الجبال، ووجد الكثير من الحطام.
It was, you know, going through the 12 Chinese provinces,
كما تعلمون، كان علينا المرور ب12 مقاطعة صينية.
this was before China was open in '87.
كان ذلك قبل فتح الصين في 87'.
And we succeeded to meet in the middle
ونجحنا في التقابل في المنتصف.
to say goodbye.
لنودع بعضنا البعض.
And then our relationship stopped.
ثم انتهت علاقتنا.
And now, it completely changed how I see the public.
والآن، تغيرت نظرتي كليا عن كيفية رؤيتي للجمهور.
And one very important piece I made in those days
والعرض المهم الذي قمت به في تلك الأيام
was "Balkan Baroque."
كان "بلقان باروك".
And this was the time of the Balkan Wars,
وكان ذلك الوقت لحروب البلقان،
and I wanted to create some very strong, charismatic image,
وأردت أن أخلق صورة شخصية جذابة وقوية،
something that could serve for any war at any time,
شيء يمكن أن يُستعمل في أي حرب وفي أي وقت،
because the Balkan Wars are now finished, but there's always some war, somewhere.
لأن حروب البلقان قد انتهت الآن، ولكن توجد دائما حرب ما في مكان ما،
So here I am washing
اذن ها أنا ذا أغسل
two and a half thousand dead, big, bloody cow bones.
2.5 آلاف عظم كبيرة ومُغطاة بالدماء لأبقار ميتة.
You can't wash the blood, you never can wash shame off the wars.
لا تستطيع أن تغسل الدم، ولا أن تمحي عار الحروب.
So I'm washing this six hours, six days, and wars are coming off these bones,
إذن أغسل هذه العظام لمدة 6 ساعات 6 أيام والحروب ما تزال تُخلّف هذه العظام،
and becoming possible -- an unbearable smell.
وأصبحت رائحتها لا تُطاق.
But then something stays in the memory.
ولكن شيء ما يعلق بالذاكرة.
I want to show you the one who really changed my life,
أريد أن أريكم الشيء الذي غير حياتي،
and this was the performance in MoMa, which I just recently made.
وذلك كان العرض بمتحف الفن الحديث، والذي قمت به مؤخرا.
This performance -- when I said to the curator,
هذا العرض -- عندما قلت للمشرف،
"I'm just going to sit at the chair,
"إنني سأجلس على الكرسي،
and there will be an empty chair at the front,
وسيكون هناك كرسي فارغ أمامي،
and anybody from the public can come and sit as long as they want."
ويمكن لأي أحد من الجماهير أن يأتي ويجلس على ذلك الكرسي قدر ما يشاء."
The curator said to me,
قال لي المشرف،
"That's ridiculous, you know, this is New York,
"هذا سخيف، أنت تعرفين، هذه نيويورك،
this chair will be empty,
سيكون الكرسي فارغا،
nobody has time to sit in front of you."
لا أحد لديه الوقت للجلوس أمامك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I sit for three months.
ولكنني جلست لمدة 3 أشهر.
And I sit everyday, eight hours --
كل يوم لمدة 8 ساعات --
the opening of the museum --
عندما يكون المتحف مفتوحا لهذه المدة --
and 10 hours on Friday when the museum is open 10 hours,
و 10 ساعات يوم الجمعة عندما يُفتح المتحف لمدة 10 ساعات،
and I never move.
ولا أتحرك أبدا.
And I removed the table and I'm still sitting,
وأزلت الطاولة ولازلت جالسة،
and this changed everything.
وهذا غير كل شيء.
This performance, maybe 10 or 15 years ago --
هذا العرض، ربما 10 أو 15 سنة الماضية --
nothing would have happened.
لم يكن ليحدث شيء.
But the need of people to actually experience something different,
ولكن حاجة الأشخاص لتجربة شيء مختلف،
the public was not anymore the group --
لم يعد الجمهور المستهدف هو مجموعة --
relation was one to one.
وإنما العلاقة أصبحت واحد لواحد.
I was watching these people, they would come and sit in front of me,
كنت أشاهد هؤلاء الأشخاص، كان من الممكن أن يأتوا ويجلسوا أمامي،
but they would have to wait for hours and hours and hours
ولكن كانوا ينتظرون لمدة ساعات وساعات وساعات
to get to this position,
للجلوس في هذا المكان،
and finally, they sit.
وفي الأخير يجلسون.
And what happened?
وما الذي جرى؟
They are observed by the other people,
تتم ملاحظتهم من قبل أشخاص آخرين،
they're photographed, they're filmed by the camera,
يتم أخذ صور لهم، وتصويرهم بواسطة الكاميرا،
they're observed by me
يتم التحديق إليهم من قبلي
and they have nowhere to escape except in themselves.
ولا يوجد أي مكان يهربون إليه ما عدى انفسهم.
And that makes a difference.
وهذا يُشكّل اختلافا.
There was so much pain and loneliness,
كان هناك الكثير من الألم والوحدة،
there's so much incredible things when you look in somebody else's eyes,
توجد أشياء لا تصدّق عندما تُحدّق في عيني شخص ما،
because in the gaze with that total stranger,
لأنه في تلك النظرة مع شخص غريب،
that you never even say one word -- everything happened.
والذي لم تخبره أي كلمة قط -- حصلت الكثير من الأشياء.
And I understood when I stood up from that chair after three months,
وفهمت عندما غادرت ذلك الكرسي بعد ثلاثة أشهر،
I am not the same anymore.
بأنني لست نفس الشخص سابقا.
And I understood that I have a very strong mission,
وفهمت بأنني أملك مهمة كبيرة،
that I have to communicate this experience
وهي أن أُبلّغ هذه التجربة
to everybody.
للجميع.
And this is how, for me, was born the idea
وهكذا نشأت لديا فكرة،
to have an institute of immaterial performing arts.
امتلاك معهد لفنون العروض غير المادية.
Because thinking about immateriality,
لأن التفكير في العرض
performance is time-based art.
غير المادي هو فن أساسه الوقت.
It's not like a painting.
لا يُشبه الطلي.
You have the painting on the wall, the next day it's there.
تضع الطلاء على الحائط، فتجده غدا في مكانه.
Performance, if you are missing it, you only have the memory,
إذا فوت عرضا، ستكون لديك مجرد ذكرى،
or the story of somebody else telling you,
أو القصة التي سمعتها من شخص آخر،
but you actually missed the whole thing.
ولكنك في الحقيقة فوت العرض بأكمله.
So you have to be there.
اذن يجب عليك الحضور.
And in my point, if you talk about immaterial art,
وفي نظري، إذا تحدثت عن الفن غير المادي،
music is the highest -- absolutely highest art of all,
فالموسيقى هي أحسن فن -- على الإطلاق،
because it's the most immaterial.
لأنها أكثر فن غير مادي.
And then after this is performance, and then everything else.
ثم يأتي العرض، وثم كلّ شيء.
That's my subjective way.
هذا ترتيبي الشخصي.
This institute is going to happen in Hudson, upstate New York,
سيتم تأسيس المعهد بهدسن، شمال ولاية نيويورك،
and we are trying to build with Rem Koolhaas, an idea.
ونحن في طور محاولة بناء فكرة مع ريم خولاس.
And it's very simple.
وهي بسيطة جدا.
If you want to get experience, you have to give me your time.
إذا أردت أن تكون لديك تجربة، عليك أن تُعطيني من وقتك.
You have to sign the contract before you enter the building,
عليك أن تُمضي العقد قبل دخولك للبناية،
that you will spend there a full six hours,
بأنك ستُمضي هناك 6 ساعات،
you have to give me your word of honor.
عليك أن تُعطيني كلمة شرف.
It's something so old-fashioned,
إنه شيء قديم جدا،
but if you don't respect your own word of honor and you leave before --
ولكن في صورة عدم احترامك لكلمة الشرف وتُغادر قبل الوقت --
that's not my problem.
هذه ليست مشكلتي.
But it's six hours, the experience.
ولكن التجربة تدوم 6 ساعات.
And then after you finish, you get a certificate of accomplishment,
وبعد انتهائك، سوف تحصل على شهادة لإتمامك هذه المهمة،
so get home and frame it if you want.
وتعود بها إلى البيت وتضعها في إطار إذا أردت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is orientation hall.
هذا البهو لإرشادك.
The public comes in, and the first thing you have to do is dress in lab coats.
يأتي الجمهور، وأول شيء عليك القيام به هو لبس معطف المختبر.
It's this importance
هذا مهم لكي تتحول من
of stepping from being just a viewer into experimenter.
مجرد مُشاهد إلى شخص للتجارب.
And then you go to the lockers
ثم تتجه نحو الخزائن
and you put your watch, your iPhone, your iPod, your computer
لتضع ساعتك والآي فون وآي باد وحاسوبك المحمول
and everything digital, electronic.
وكل جهاز رقمي أو إلكتروني.
And you are getting free time for yourself for the first time.
ستحصل على وقت فراغ لنفسك لأول مرة.
Because there is nothing wrong with technology,
لأنه لا يوجد خطأ بالتكنولوجيا،
our approach to technology is wrong.
ولكن منهجنا المتعلق بالتكنولوجيا غير صحيح.
We are losing the time we have for ourselves.
نحن نُضيع الوقت المُخصّص لنا.
This is an institute to actually give you back this time.
مهمّة هذا المعهد هي أن تُعيد لك هذا الوقت.
So what you do here,
إذن ما الذي تقوم به هنا،
first you start slow walking, you start slowing down.
أولا تبدأ في المشي ببطء، ثم تبدأ في التباطؤ في خطواتك.
You're going back to simplicity.
وترجع إلى البساطة.
After slow walking, you're going to learn how to drink water --
بعد المشي ببطء، سوف تتعلم كيفية شرب الماء --
very simple, drinking water for maybe half an hour.
بكل بساطة، شرب الماء لمدة نصف ساعة تقريبا.
After this, you're going to the magnet chamber,
بعد ذلك، سوف تتجه لغرفة المغناطيس،
where you're going to create some magnet streams on your body.
حيث ستخلق نوعا من التيارات المغناطيسية على جسدك.
Then after this, you go to crystal chamber.
ثم تتجه نحو غرفة البلور.
After crystal chamber, you go to eye-gazing chamber,
وبعد غرفة البلور ستتجه نحو غرفة تحديق العين،
after eye-gazing chamber, you go to a chamber where you are lying down.
وبعد غرفة تحديق العين، ستتجه نحو غرفة الإستلقاء.
So it's the three basic positions of the human body,
اذن توجد الوضعيات الثلاث الأساسية لجسم الإنسان،
sitting, standing and lying.
الجلوس والوقوف والإستلقاء.
And slow walking.
والمشيء ببطء.
And there is a sound chamber.
وتوجد غرفة الصوت.
And then after you've seen all of this,
ثم بعد رؤيتكم لجميع تلك الغرف،
and prepared yourself mentally and physically,
واستعدادكم معنويا وماديا،
then you are ready to see something with a long duration,
اذن أنتم الآن مستعدون لرؤية شيء يدوم مدة طويلة،
like in immaterial art.
كفنّ غير مادي.
It can be music, it can be opera, it can be a theater piece,
يمكن أن يكون موسيقى أو أوبرا أو قطعة مسرحية،
it can be film, it can be video dance.
أو فيلم أو فيديو رقص.
You go to the long duration chairs because now you are comfortable.
اذهب إلى الكراسي المخصصة للمدة الطويلة لأنك الآن مرتاح.
In the long duration chairs,
في الكراسي المخصصة للمدة الطويلة،
you're transported to the big place where you're going to see the work.
سوف يتم تحويلك إلى مكان فسيح أين يمكنك رؤية العمل.
And if you fall asleep,
وفي صورة نومك،
which is very possible because it's been a long day,
والذي من الممكن أن يحدث لأنه كان يوما طويلا،
you're going to be transported to the parking lot.
سيتم نقلك إلى موقف السيارات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you know, sleeping is very important.
وكما تعلمون، النوم مهم جدا.
In sleeping, you're still receiving art.
خلال نومك، ستظلّ تستقبل الفن.
So in the parking lot you stay for a certain amount of time,
اذن ستمكث في موقف السيارات لمدة من الوقت،
and then after this you just, you know, go back,
ثم بعد ذلك، كما تعلم، ستعود،
you see more of the things you like to see
ستشاهد أشياء أكثر من تلك التي تُحبّذ مشاهدتها
or go home with your certificate.
أو تعود إلى المنزل حاملا شهادتك.
So this institute right now is virtual.
إذن هذا المعهد حاليا هو افتراضي.
Right now, I am just making my institute in Brazil,
حاليا، أقوم بتشييد معهدي بالبرازيل،
then it's going to be in Australia,
ثم سيكون ذلك بأستراليا،
then it's coming here, to Canada and everywhere.
ثم هنا، إلى كندا وفي كل مكان.
And this is to experience a kind of simple method,
وهذا لتجربة نوع من الطرق البسيطة،
how you go back to simplicity in your own life.
كيف تعود إلى البساطة بحياتك.
Counting rice will be another thing.
سيكون عدّ حبّات الأرزّ شيئا آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, if you count rice you can make life, too.
أنتم تعلمون، إذا قمت بعدّ حبّات الأرزّ، يمكنك العيش أيضا.
How to count rice for six hours?
كيف يمكنك عدّ حبّات الأرزّ لمدّة 6 ساعات؟
It's incredibly important.
هذا حتما مهمّ جدّا بشكل لا يُصدّق.
You know, you go through this whole range of being bored, being angry,
كما تعلمون، ستمرّ بمجموعة من الأحاسيس القلق والغضب،
being completely frustrated, not finishing the amount of rice you're counting.
الشعور بالإحباط الكلّي، عدم إنهاء عدّ حبّات الأرز.
And then this unbelievable amount of peace you get
ثم ذلك الشعور بالسلام
when satisfying work is finished --
عندما تنهي عملك --
or counting sand in the desert.
أو عدّ حبات الرمل بالصحراء.
Or having the sound-isolated situation --
أو وضعية عزل الصوت --
that you have headphones, that you don't hear anything,
امتلاكك لسماعات، عدم سماعك لأي شيء،
and you're just there together without sound,
وأنتم هناك مع بعضكم من دون سماع أي صوت،
with the people experiencing silence, just the simple silence.
مع مجموعة من الأشخاص تُجرّبون الصمت.
We are always doing things we like in our life.
نحن دائما نقوم بأشياء نحبها في حياتنا.
And this is why you're not changing.
ولذلك أنتم لا تتغيرون.
You do things in life --
أنت تقوم بأشياء في الحياة --
it's just nothing happens if you always do things the same way.
لن يتغير شيء إذا كنت تقوم بالأشياء بنفس الطريقة.
But my method is to do things I'm afraid of, the things I fear,
ولكن تكمن طريقتي في القيام بأشياء تُخيفني،
the things I don't know,
أشياء لا أعرفها،
to go to territory that nobody's ever been.
الذهاب إلى أماكن لم أزرها من قبل.
And then also to include the failure.
بما في ذلك الفشل.
I think failure is important
أعتقد أن الفشل مهم
because if you go, if you experiment, you can fail.
لأنك إذا ذهبت وجربت يمكن أن تفشل.
If you don't go into that area and you don't fail,
وإن لم تذهب إلى ذلك المكان ولا تفشل،
you are actually repeating yourself over and over again.
فأنت تعيد نفس الشيء مرارا وتكرارا.
And I think that human beings right now need a change,
وأعتقد أن البشر الآن في حاجة إلى التغيير،
and the only change to be made is a personal level change.
والتغيير الوحيد الذي يجب القيام به هو على الصعيد الشخصي.
You have to make the change on yourself.
يجب أن تغير من نفسك.
Because the only way to change consciousness
لأن الطريقة الوحيدة لتغيير الوعي
and to change the world around us,
وتغيير العالم حولنا،
is to start with yourself.
هي البدء بنفسك.
It's so easy to criticize how it's different,
من السهل نقد اختلاف،
the things in the world and they're not right,
الأشياء بالعالم وعدم صحتها،
and the governments are corrupted and there's hunger in the world
والفساد بالحكومات والجوع في العالم
and there's wars -- the killing.
والحروب --
But what we do on the personal level --
ولكن ما نقوم به على الصعيد الشخصي --
what is our contribution to this whole thing?
ماهي مساهمتنا في كل هذا؟
Can you turn to your neighbor, the one you don't know,
هل يمكنك الذهاب إلى جارك، الذي لا تعرفه،
and look at them for two full minutes in their eyes, right now?
وتحدق في عينيه لمدة دقيقتين كاملتين الآن؟
(Chatter)
(ثرثرة)
I'm asking two minutes of your time, that's so little.
أنا أطلب فقط دقيقتين من وقتكم، هذا قصير جدا.
Breathe slowly, don't try to blink, don't be self-conscious.
تنفس ببطء، لا تُحاول غلق عينيك،
Be relaxed.
لا تخجل، كن مرتاحا.
And just look a complete stranger in your eyes, in his eyes.
وكن غريبا في عينيه وعينيك.
(Silence)
(صمت)
Thank you for trusting me.
شكرا لكم للوثوق بي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you.
كريس أندرسون: شكرا لك.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لك.